<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DH:Personal</title>
    <description>A blog of a person learning things others long ago understood.</description>
    <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://dhepworth.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 15:29:56 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 15:29:56 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Being invisible</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;When we moved into our new house, my wife and I decided to purchase a couple seed packs of flowers to put in a garden in the back yard. We chose to purchase native wildflowers; we thought they would have the greatest chance of surviving and the variety of seeds included promised to provide a lot of colors and shapes of blossoms. We were overwhelmed by the assortment when they bloomed in the spring, and marveled at how beautiful and unique each flower was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was potentially even more stunning to us was the classification of “weed” for most of what grew. What we saw as incredibly valuable was deemed by others to be a nuisance, a plant worthy of destruction. We could not fully understand how someone could see such a gorgeous assortment and classify them in such low esteem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The realization that value could be so wide in its interpretation was on my mind as I considered my internal image of myself. From my youth I have worked to lessen my consideration of my own value, thinking it a virtue to self-deprecate. I have self-assigned my personal contributions to work assignments and relationships to be of such a minimal worth because I thought it would be prideful to believe or accept any other interpretation. I ignored the compliments of others. I dismissed the evaluations of my worth unless it was at least as bad as my own estimation. I thought I was being a better person by hating myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet as I considered my prized flowers that others would deem repulsive, I wondered if my self-perception could be incorrect. Could I be poisoning my life with such a crushing view of myself? Could I be assigning the status of “weed” to my life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years I have battled the dissonance of wanting to be successful, which would result in some level of notoriety, with the ingrained view that any level of fame is a potential moral failing because being noticed could inevitably lead to pride and destruction of self. I chose invisibility as the default: better to be the wallflower and be a “good person” than to be popular and turn out a monster. Yet I found no joy in being unknown, for anonymity seemed cursed with an impotence to improve the lives of others. I was no superhero with vast caches of money or super-human abilities to hide my identity while greatly impacting others; instead, I was just hiding in the shadows of my community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How was this misery and near-constant depression anything but a wasted life? I was making little of the changes that I aimed to make as a young adult. I was severely dependent on a few friendships that I constantly chided myself for having and regularly believed to be a case of pity for a slug like me. I was regularly rejecting the value that others assigned to me, inadvertently insulting them by throwing away the compliments they sent to me was a poor judgement of my character. I was being frivolous with the gifts of friendships and community because I thought it better to deprive myself of their joys — even guilty for feeling any sense of happiness. What a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now aim to see my life as I see my flowers: they are valuable just by existing, waiting to be seen by others who also see their worth. They will not be treasured by hiding their petals: they must take the risk of being harmed or misrepresented by boldly throwing open their blossoms and calling for the attention of the creatures who will love them. There is no virtue in hiding; there is no absolute moral good in being invisible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The memories I hold closest to me are the ones where people noticed me and loved me. There was a measure of shame associated with enjoying those memories, because I felt that it was wrong to be loved — I was, after all, supposed to avoid such feelings lest I fall to pride and vanity. But how can I find value in other humans if the one human I know the most — myself — I hate with such passion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to see myself, like a flower, as being worthy of love. I know that I am not going to be loved by all, just as a weed may be culled by some and kept by others, but I think that the goal of finding some who see your beauty is worth the pain of being undervalued by others. I think that if I can start seeing myself as valuable and accepting that others can feel the same, I will be far more capable of sharing that same kind of love to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a simple flower can find the courage to be visible, why not I?&lt;/p&gt;

            
                
                    &lt;h4&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
                    &lt;ul&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newsweek.com/trans-man-broken-men-1817169&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;I’m a Trans Man. I Didn’t Realize How Broken Men Are&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/t/ZT8N6PSB9/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nihilism for Men — @nononsensespirituality / TikTok&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.robkhenderson.com/p/the-age-30-crisis-and-seasons-of&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Age 30 Crisis and Seasons of a Man’s Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://anuatluru.com/blog/trophyjobs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Trophy Jobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/encountering-america/201407/what-s-wrong-being-cool&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;What’s Wrong With Being Cool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://genagorlin.substack.com/p/death-is-the-default&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Death Is the Default&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/articles/89511/robert-frost-the-road-not-taken&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robert Frost: “The Road Not Taken”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                
            
            &lt;p class=&quot;embedtool&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/g46mdiqDcy4&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;Charles Bukowski&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g46mdiqDcy4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dreamlessly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;details class=&quot;m1&quot;&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Poem contents&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Old grey-haired waitresses&lt;br&gt;
In cafes at night&lt;br&gt;
Have given it up,&lt;br&gt;
And as i walk down sidewalks of light&lt;br&gt;
And look into windows of nursing homes&lt;br&gt;
I can see that it is no longer with them.&lt;br&gt;
I see people sitting on park benches&lt;br&gt;
And i can see by the way they sit and look&lt;br&gt;
That it is gone.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I see people driving cars&lt;br&gt;
And I see by the way&lt;br&gt;
They drive their cars&lt;br&gt;
That they neither love nor are loved –&lt;br&gt;
Nor do they consider sex.&lt;br&gt;
It is all forgotten&lt;br&gt;
Like an old movie.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I see people in department stores and supermarkets&lt;br&gt;
Walking down aisles&lt;br&gt;
Buying things&lt;br&gt;
And i can see by the way their clothing&lt;br&gt;
Fits them and by the way they walk&lt;br&gt;
And by their faces and their eyes&lt;br&gt;
That they care for nothing&lt;br&gt;
And that nothing cares for them.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I see a hundred people a day&lt;br&gt;
Who have given up entirely.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;If I go to the racetrack  or a sporting event&lt;br&gt;
I can see thousands that feel for nothing&lt;br&gt;
Or no one&lt;br&gt;
And get no feeling back.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Everywhere I see those who&lt;br&gt;
Crave nothing but food, shelter, and clothing;&lt;br&gt;
They concentrate on that,&lt;br&gt;
Dreamlessly&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I do not understand why these people do not&lt;br&gt;
vanish&lt;br&gt;
I do not understand why these people do not&lt;br&gt;
expire&lt;br&gt;
Why the clouds do not murder them&lt;br&gt;
Or why the dogs do not murder them&lt;br&gt;
Or why the flowers and the children do not murder them,&lt;br&gt;
I do not understand.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I suppose they are murdered&lt;br&gt;
Yet i can’t adjust to the&lt;br&gt;
Fact of them&lt;br&gt;
Because they are so many.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Each day,&lt;br&gt;
Each night,&lt;br&gt;
There are more of them&lt;br&gt;
In the subways and&lt;br&gt;
In the buildings and&lt;br&gt;
In the parks&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;They feel no terror&lt;br&gt;
At not loving&lt;br&gt;
Or at not&lt;br&gt;
Being loved&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;So many many many&lt;br&gt;
Of my fellow creatures&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music:&lt;/strong&gt; Max Richter — &lt;em&gt;On the Nature of Daylight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Tom O’Bedlam (SpokenVerse)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Video:&lt;/strong&gt; Pexels.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;Christine Emba — The Washington Post&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2023/07/10/christine-emba-masculinity-new-model/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Men are lost. Here’s a map out of the wilderness.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Worrying about the state of our men is an American tradition. But today’s problems are real and well documented.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still regularly go through my own identity crisis of what it means to be a man. I don’t want to follow the traditional expectations of masculinity because many of them are troubling to me, but I’m still trying to figure out if there is anything unique about being a man outside of that tradition. I am happy that I am a human, but I want to find something about manhood that feels good to have without feeling bad for those who lack it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a woman is not only impressive because of the physical attributes that can support life from within, but also the bravery and strength that comes from the ailments that occur from such a system. Menstruation, hormonal changes, pain, and disease is such a constant issue for women. I feel humbled about sharing my minor back pain from nerve damage when I consider what women face on a far more frequent basis. I don’t face the type of oppression, doubt, or danger that women do in all aspects of their life, so my minor inconveniences faced in life feel foolish to ever discuss. I have been given one of the easiest lives just by being born who I am, so should I feel any sense of accomplishment? I struggle to find a lot of who I am worthy of pride; very often I feel undeserving or shameful of what I have been provided just by being born a man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a nice person can come from any sex — it’s the bare minimum I expect from any person. I want to find the element of manhood that is unique to that sex that brings goodness to the world and beauty to its existence, but feel I must continue searching.&lt;/p&gt;

        </description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2023/08/19/being-invisible.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2023/08/19/being-invisible.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is church?</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does the average American Evangelical attend church? What are their goals, and do they find those goals met?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My history in the Christian church began in my childhood. Most of the sermons I heard came from my father, standing near (but not behind — his personal preference) the pulpit of whatever church we were attending at the time. My father pastored several churches throughout my time in the family home, sometimes in church buildings and sometimes in the house of one of the people in attendance. I love my experiences in those years and the communities that formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a bit of an adversarial approach to other churches in the community. I matured in a somewhat sequestered monoculture, often not being exposed to denominations or viewpoints that didn’t match those of my mentors. As a result, I saw anyone else who disagreed with me as being sadly misinformed to morally degraded, so I kept to my community because I was certain that we were what remained of “true Christians”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I retained this mindset even after leaving the family home and moving across the country to Oklahoma for a job. For about a year I continued to live-stream my father’s sermons because I was certain that there was no other decent church available, even in the “Bible Belt” of Oklahoma. When I finally felt it was time to build a community of friends in my local community, I visited with deep trepidation my first non-denominational church in my life and the first non-father-led church in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I had a few prickly moments of uncertainty about the methods of the sermons and the culture of and practices in the church, I discovered that I appreciated learning different views on Bible verses and stories. I began to better understand the differences between denominations and doctrines and why they were a struggle for so many. I met my wife at this time and we both began regularly attending this church with our friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually we began attending a small group, where we had our own little Bible study time and then casual conversation around a few snacks. The church didn’t have a good structure around small groups, so when that small group’s leaders chose to step away from their roles, the process to reintegrate felt chaotic and mostly hopeless. After finding little success in forming a new group and tiring of the sermons that had begun to feel confined in their scope and study, we moved to a new church farther down the street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new church didn’t have small groups outside of church hours but instead had “Sunday School”, in the sense that the small groups attended either right before or after the sermon on Sunday. This felt like a step backward in terms of building a community, so it was on to the next church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new church had wildly different views on Christian doctrine, so that was a short-lived visit. Besides, it was time to move to Houston for a new job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process continued in Houston. The experiences were the same when we returned to Oklahoma. I shared with my wife my beloved memories of childhood church attendance, but we couldn’t find a match in culture in any of the churches I attended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was my childhood mentality of the American church being weak being proven true? Had I made a decade-long mistake in choosing to give any one of these churches a chance? Were the only good churches those found in my past? Or was there perhaps a deeper problem of which I was only now becoming aware?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;readmore&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;church-as-a-place-of-learning&quot;&gt;Church as a place of learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have many deeply important memories of the intense Biblical debates I observed or in which I participated during my childhood. My father was often involved in them, and through him I formed much of what I believed to be true about the Bible and the manner in which it should be interpreted. Effectively starting my life as an empty vessel, I filled it with the teaching of my father and those around him, and I heard that teaching spoken often. When I left home I felt confident in my righteousness and certain that what I believed was the most obvious viewpoint one could have and that all good people would share that view. What I discovered in other churches deeply challenged my understanding of the Christian community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other denominations and viewpoints within the Evangelical Christian churches weren’t based on malicious interpretations as I had expected. People weren’t actively rebelling against my view of the Bible as I had declared in my past. Every church member was behaving in a way that they thought was proper and striving to meet the standards that they believed were set for them through the text of the Bible and the church culture that they preferred. Denominational differences were based on reasoning that appeared sound for both sides. My understanding of the Bible was just one of many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the diversity of opinion was exciting, it got me wondering: if all these groups read the same text but came to different and equally confident conclusions, then how could I really claim to be certain that what I believed was the best interpretation? I didn’t know these viewpoints existed until I started visiting these churches and I had only seen a small selection, but one of them had to be true, right? It seemed mathematically conclusive that at least one of the churches in existence had the fully proper interpretation of the Bible. Was one of those churches in my proximity, or were all the churches around me teaching at least one falsehood?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/960863-until-every-soul-is-freely-permitted-to-investigate-every-book&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is amazing to me that a difference of opinion upon subjects that we know nothing with certainty about, should make us hate, persecute, and despise each other. Why a difference of opinion upon predestination, or the trinity, should make people imprison and burn each other seems beyond the comprehension of man; and yet in all countries where Christians have existed, they have destroyed each other to the exact extent of their power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Robert G. Ingersoll — &lt;em&gt;Mistakes of Moses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A multitude of questions started to flow through my mind, overwhelming me and leading to great distress. What were the pastors not telling me? Was a pastor from a seminary a more reliable or a more biased source? Was a confident pastor an ignorant one or a learned one? If I was visiting churches looking for one that seemed “right” to me, was I really looking to learn or just confirm my own presuppositions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major moment of change for me was when I learned of the long-fought debate between people who based their faith on free will versus those who believed in determinism. My early interactions in this area were watching debates on YouTube between James White and Leighton Flowers, who passionately and regularly sniped back and forth about the exclusively correct state of their opposing interpretations of the Bible. Mr. White tended to boast of the ancestral credentials to his viewpoint, following the lineage of the view back to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/06/19/how-st-augustine-invented-sex&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aurelius Augustinus&lt;/a&gt;, an angst-ridden man who tortured himself with worries about his moral state with God, and Mr. Flowers’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Potters-Promise-Biblical-Traditional-Soteriology/dp/0692561846&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;viewpoint&lt;/a&gt; which focused more on how God couldn’t be a loving god while also purposely creating people intended to be doomed to eternal punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was alarming to me in watching and reading their reasoning was discovering that &lt;em&gt;they were both correct&lt;/em&gt;. They had very good points on which to base their views and verse after verse to support them. The whole reason the debate had continued for so long was because the writers in the Bible &lt;em&gt;also had differing views&lt;/em&gt;. The disagreements between the founders of Christianity are documented within the Bible, never mind the centuries of councils and denominations that formed based on those differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Misquoting_Jesus&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, a number of passages in our surviving manuscripts appear to embody the apologetic concerns of the early Christians, especially as these relate to the founder of their faith, Jesus himself. Just as with theological conflicts in the early church, the question of the role of women, and the controversies with the Jews, so too with the disputes raging between Christians and their cultured despisers among the pagans: all of these controversies came to affect the texts that were eventually to become part of the book that we now call the New Testament, as this book—or rather, this set of books—was compiled by nonprofessional scribes in the second and third centuries, and occasionally came to be altered in light of the contexts of their day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Bart D. Ehrman — &lt;em&gt;Misquoting Jesus: The Story Behind Who Changed the Bible and Why&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t find the answers to my questions in any of the churches I attended; instead, I only witnessed apologetics for one position or the other, argued in a vacuum with the opposition as a boogeyman. Every verse was bent and twisted to fit one harmonious view, only to be distorted in the opposite way to fit the contrasting view in the church across the street. One &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/nbc-out/out-news/texas-pastor-says-gay-people-shot-back-head-shocking-sermon-rcna32748&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;church could be lead by a pastor wishing to kill gay people&lt;/a&gt; while another &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brandan_Robertson&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;church could be employing a gay pastor&lt;/a&gt;. Some pastors might advocate for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://southsidechurchofchrist.com/sermons/hellfire-and-brimstone.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;eternal torture of sinners&lt;/a&gt; for their finite faults committed during their life; some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2012/11/26/the-hell-raiser-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;that there is no Hell&lt;/a&gt;; others might claim that &lt;a href=&quot;https://reknew.org/2008/01/the-case-for-annihilationism/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hell is misunderstood&lt;/a&gt;; some might attest that the issue is moot because everyone &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kOzmwGmiDHQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;can&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universalist_Church_of_America&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;will&lt;/a&gt; eventually go to Heaven. Each view would claim divine authority and would have enough Biblical support to be convincing to &lt;em&gt;those seeking that particular viewpoint&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began to understand that if I were to stay within just the learning experience of a church sermon, I would have to accept that the source of my understanding of the Bible would likely largely stay within myself. I was like every other church member: unconsciously forming the interpretation of the Bible based on a personal worldview and then seeking out a church that would confirm that view through selective reading of Bible passages. That is a comforting state to many and one that I experienced for many years of my life, but I wanted to understand more. I was worried that I wasn’t going to find a reliable informational source within the walls of a church. I sought out wider opinions from scholars, historians, and philosophers who had a greater amount of experience in not only the matters of the Bible but the context in which it was written and the societies around it during its formation. I wanted a more scientific method of discovery where opinions could be tested in a more public forum. Once I realized that there was so much more to learn about the Bible than what one denomination or another could offer or allow, and that deeper thought was actually rather widely available, I knew that a church would likely never again be a place of learning for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;church-as-a-community-center&quot;&gt;Church as a community center&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When moving to a new neighborhood where no friends or family live, one might ask a local how they found and formed their own friendships. In Oklahoma, the primary response one should expect is to attend a church. Church is often where people claim to have met some of their deepest and most meaningful connections. In my experience, many people might be saying it, but few are living it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A church sermon isn’t really the place for one to have a conversation with even the person in the next seat, so church leaders came up with the solution: church, but smaller, in the form of meetings with a limited selection of church members who share common interests or stages of life. Nearly every church I’ve visited has encouraged the assembly of smaller groups of church members to meet within the church building on Sunday or within each other’s homes during the week. Usually the suggestion is to attend all options provided: a community group and a sermon on Sunday morning and a small group at some point during the week. These groups usually convene in the form of a “Bible study”, where a group leader reads the Bible and then pilots discussion afterwards. Sometimes the studies involve the same book as what is being discussed in the sermon on Sunday morning, and sometimes the sermon itself is the focus of discussion. The purpose of these groups is to build friendships with a selection of church members and to keep the Bible as a priority throughout the week. Pastors will often say that the sermon may be a place where someone gets to learn about the faith, but that the effects of that sermon and the community to support the changes that it produces are found within a community group and small group. One pastor I heard went so far as to say that very little value could be produced from exclusively attending church on Sunday morning; community groups were that essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of these community groups is to build deep friendships with the others who attend, share painful moments from the week with them, and then receive or give encouragement. But these aren’t friends, they’re strangers. Meeting for an hour or two a week &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0265407518761225&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;will not produce friendships&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0265407518761225&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casual friendships emerge around 30 hr, followed by friendships around 50 hr. Good friendships begin to emerge after 140 hr. Best friendships do not emerge until after 300 hr of time spent. Whether spending 30 or 600 hr of time together, the percentage of all relationships formed in closed systems (e.g., work, school) remains relatively constant. Logistic regressions offered 3-point estimates: 94 hr when acquaintances become casual friends, 164 hr when casual friends become friends, and 219 hr when friends become good/best friends. These numbers are likely conservative estimates due to the inclusion of both closed system and chosen relationships and due to the retrospective nature of the study. It is quite likely that the friendship status transitioned to a higher level before these cut-point estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Jeffrey A. Hall — &lt;em&gt;How many hours does it take to make a friend?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the community groups that tend to succeed don’t prosper because the members met &lt;em&gt;in the community group&lt;/em&gt;, they prosper because the people attending met and became good friends &lt;em&gt;before forming their own community group&lt;/em&gt;. The community group doesn’t appear to regularly be the catalyst for the formation of a community, but rather the byproduct of one built elsewhere. This pre-existing friendship makes it incredibly hard for new community group members to break through, either requiring a separate clique of new members becoming acquaintances or forever feeling like an outsider among the community. If there isn’t enough growth within the community — and due to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/19/opinion/religion-america.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;decreasing numbers of churchgoers&lt;/a&gt;, that is often the case — then the general expectation I have for community groups is the slow withering of new members who quietly leave and never return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Church isn’t the place to build community, but it’s often cited as such. What options are available to those who no longer see church in that way and who seek an alternative? The choices seem limited, in part because enough churchgoers see church as the ultimate source of community, rejecting many other legitimate and perhaps superior methods available to them even if their preferred meeting choice of a church isn’t leading to a thriving base of friendships. For some, leaving that hub to instead experience long periods of loneliness and uncertainty is too painful; but for others like me, staying within a broken system is even worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;church-as-a-cultural-example&quot;&gt;Church as a cultural example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/10426666-in-the-end-doug-wilson-john-piper-mark-driscoll-james&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, Doug Wilson, John Piper, Mark Driscoll, James Dobson, Doug Phillips, and John Eldredge all preached a mutually reinforcing vision of Christian masculinity—of patriarchy and submission, sex and power. It was a vision that promised protection for women but left women without defense, one that worshiped power and turned a blind eye to justice, and one that transformed the Jesus of the Gospels into an image of their own making. Though rooted in different traditions and couched in different styles, their messages blended together to become the dominant chord in the cacophony of evangelical popular culture. And they had been right all along. The militant Christian masculinity they practiced and preached did indelibly shape both family and nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Kristin Kobes DuMez — &lt;em&gt;Jesus and John Wayne: How White Evangelicals Corrupted a Faith and Fractured a Nation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up I heard Christians say that churches make up (or should make up) for the social services that are lacking from state and federal government, so that charitable giving to churches was a net good as that money was then sent out into the community. &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.yahoo.com/news/conservative-myth-social-safety-net-120000203.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;That belief may not be fully grounded in reality,&lt;/a&gt; but it is a useful example for the point that I’m trying to make. Churches are often depicted, at least in the areas where I’ve lived, as a moral example to the rest of the world. Real love, guidance, companionship, and mentoring can be found only in a church, or so the claims go. I used to believe there may be some credence to these claims, but I find them pretty dubious now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Churches claim moral supremacy, but they regularly prove themselves to be incredibly dangerous outlets for repressed emotions. Despite the origin of Christianity being founded within the oppressed and weak, modern churches share a legacy and continued reputation for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2014/05/religious-right-real-origins-107133/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;bigotry and hatred of minorities&lt;/a&gt;. Pastors regularly advocate for a political party that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/republicans-voting-against-their-own-interests-its_b_596cec66e4b07f87578e6ab7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;actively harms its constituents&lt;/a&gt; with a leader who &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Trump#Misogyny_and_allegations_of_sexual_misconduct&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;flagrantly violates the lifestyle&lt;/a&gt; that Christians deem acceptable to their god. Church leaders &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.msnbc.com/the-reidout/reidout-blog/illinois-catholic-church-child-abuse-rcna86289&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;regularly commit sexual assault&lt;/a&gt; against their followers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2022/06/02/1102621352/how-the-southern-baptist-convention-covered-up-its-widespread-sexual-abuse-scand&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;infrastructure exists to keep it hidden&lt;/a&gt;. Some pastors can’t manage to say the phrase &lt;a href=&quot;https://whatwouldyousay.org/should-christians-support-black-lives-matter/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“Black Lives Matter”&lt;/a&gt; without at least a caveat. During Covid-19, churches were sources of misinformation and anti-science sentiment, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thedailybeast.com/united-house-of-prayer-for-all-people-in-charlotte-north-carolina-spread-coronavirus-locals-say&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;leading to numerous deaths from super-spreader events&lt;/a&gt;. Churches offer mentoring, but not the variety that is based on science intended to aid those in need, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportskeeda.com/pop-culture/epic-cult-vibes-james-river-church-tank-video-goes-viral-leaves-internet-disbelief&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;unless one is to believe that monster trucks teach men how to be decent humans&lt;/a&gt;. One churchgoer was so frustrated by the lack of good leadership for men in his church that &lt;a href=&quot;https://truemanlifecoaching.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;he started his own non-profit&lt;/a&gt; to assist men who felt they didn’t get proper leadership from their churches. These are training tools &lt;em&gt;for men&lt;/em&gt;, by far the most favored sex in the patriarchal complementarian view most churches prefer. Women instead receive the special treatment of an extra dose of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.choosingtherapy.com/purity-culture/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;purity culture&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/06/10/us/southern-baptist-convention-sex-abuse.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;victim blaming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/10899605-ironically-complementarian-theology-claims-it-is-defending-a-plain-and&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ironically, complementarian theology claims it is defending a plain and natural interpretation of the Bible while really defending an interpretation that has been corrupted by our sinful human drive to dominate others and build hierarchies of power and oppression. I can’t think of anything less Christlike than hierarchies like these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Beth Allison Barr — &lt;em&gt;The Making of Biblical Womanhood: How the Subjugation of Women Became Gospel Truth&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over and over and &lt;em&gt;over and &lt;strong&gt;over&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; again churches do not behave in the way that they say they do. Some will admit to this hypocrisy, but refer to their poor behavior as “their mess”, a euphemism for the same type of behavior for which others outside the church are condemned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly understand why people within the churches feel that they have the best of everything within their culture, but it’s because they’ve been conditioned to never step outside of that bubble. They’ve been trained to believe that their neighbor is “the enemy” if they don’t follow the church’s exact blend of philosophical or doctrinal standards. They’ve been indoctrinated to never seek answers outside of a certain circle of speakers, even though there is an abundance of scholarship available for free to anyone with a library card or an internet connection. Christians have been told to live in constant fear by the very people helping to engender that anxiety, and to give their money and their bodies to the cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-church&quot;&gt;What is church?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to be able to honestly answer the question I raised in the title of this post, but I know I’m terribly biased these days against the church. I didn’t find that it followed through on its promises and I don’t like feeling lied to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/A2ttSv7I9HY&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Churches are spaces where one man may share his worldview in a position of authority and use an ancient collection of texts to support that position. If enough people like hearing their own worldview confidently repeated back to them, then the pastor becomes popular and the viewpoint becomes the more accepted position for moderate Christians. The text of the Bible contains sections of letters that share this tension amongst its followers, even in its early stages of formation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Timothy%204:3-4&amp;amp;version=NASB&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the time will come when they will not tolerate sound doctrine; but wanting to have their ears tickled, they will accumulate for themselves teachers in accordance with their own desires, and they will turn their ears away from the truth and will turn aside to myths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;1 Timothy 4:3 (New American Standard Version)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or in this passage, where Paul, who repeatedly made the claim that his particular viewpoint was directly inspired by God and therefore the only complete and accurate viewpoint, makes this observation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+corinthians+1%3A10-12&amp;amp;version=NASB&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I urge you, brothers and sisters, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you all agree and that there be no divisions among you, but that you be made complete in the same mind and in the same judgment. For I have been informed concerning you, my brothers and sisters, by Chloe’s people, that there are quarrels among you. Now I mean this, that each one of you is saying, “I am with Paul,” or “I am with Apollos,” or “I am with Cephas,” or “I am with Christ.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;1 Corinthians 1:10–12 (New American Standard Version)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pauline view of Christianity prevailed through centuries of debate, inspiring later followers like Augustine and Martin Luther to further expand upon his foundations and build a devoted following throughout the centuries. Other viewpoints, existing within the Bible and throughout history, have fought and lost the battle for public acceptance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcion_of_Sinope&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;branded as heretical&lt;/a&gt;. That this opinion was swayed by the current events of the time is rarely accepted among Christian churches, who advocate for divine inspiration throughout generations as the reasoning for the evolving standards of the faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Churches could be a forum for discussion on how to adapt the faith to the era in which is it currently being spoken, or a safe area to discuss the Bible and the complexities of its interpretations without judgement, but it is instead a machine for dogmatic thought and unquestioning application. Questioning is doubt, and doubt that doesn’t lead to a result that the church favors is ultimately a sin, so people choose to be told what to think rather than risk being seen as a sinner. Learning about the Bible’s history outside of the walls of a church has been far more interesting to me because I’ve been able to explore all lines of thought without judgement by a pastor or community group. The result is that I have been able to understand far more about the Bible, its history, and the impact it has had on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/960965-let-us-forget-that-we-are-baptists-methodists-catholics-presbyterians&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us forget that we are Baptists, Methodists, Catholics, Presbyterians, or Free-thinkers, and remember only that we are men and women. After all, man and woman are the highest possible titles. All other names belittle us, and show that we have, to a certain extent, given up our individuality, and have consented to wear the collar of authority—that we are followers. Throwing away these names, let us examine these questions not as partisans, but as human beings with hopes and fears in common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Robert G. Ingersoll — &lt;em&gt;Mistakes of Moses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I can answer what church is by advocating for what it shouldn’t be: a hurdle to being a decent human being. As soon as a pastor or a denomination starts setting rules in place that seem to be getting in the way of being loving to others or asking difficult questions with uncomfortable answers, I believe that it’s in everyone’s best interest to choose something different to do on a Sunday morning.&lt;/p&gt;


            
                
                    &lt;h4&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
                    &lt;ul&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/2022/02/03/anxious-about-being-ignorant.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DH:Personal — I used to be anxious about being thought of as ignorant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                
            
            &lt;p class=&quot;embedtool&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZRi1mOQEXQw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;Ryan Reeves&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZRi1mOQEXQw&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Christian Fundamentalism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;What is Christian fundamentalism and when did Christians start teaching fundamentalism? The movement of Fundamentalism comes during struggles between faith and science, as the teachings of Darwin and others began to concern Christians as it appeared to undermine their understanding of the Bible. This video tells the story of the Scopes Monkey Trial, the publishing of The Christian Fundamentals, and the ensuing culture war between certain Christians and intellectual culture.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;embedtool&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rvkjqM5Gfio&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;Ryan Reeves&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rvkjqM5Gfio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Liberalism and the Church&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In the modern world we’re very comfortable with the Conservative versus Liberal splits that are part and parcel of the church, not only in the West but around the globe. We use words like “fundamentalist”, “progressive”, “liberal”, and a host of others as a way of signaling the split. But, I can say as a teacher of history, the more I look around the world today the more I realize that people tend to believe or they maybe assume that many of these splits are a product of the 20th century, or maybe they go back a good bit before that to the early enlightenment itself. Well, of either of those two extremes the history is not on their side.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2023/06/01/what-is-church.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2023/06/01/what-is-church.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hopelessness in video games</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;I used to play a lot of video games. These days I settle for some games from my Apple Arcade subscription, but I used to have many mobile consoles, several home consoles, and a gaming PC. I played many titles across a variety of platforms, filling out a list of memorable games that left a permanent impact on my life. In a recent conversation with my coworkers I started listing my favorite games and learned that the games that I have felt the most important in my life were ones that generated a feeling of hopelessness. I certainly enjoy a variety of gaming genres and story types, but the ones I can recall with fondness are the ones that made me feel the most miserable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these being my favorite games across all consoles, these are not generally the games that I return to in the brief moments where I can find time to play a game. Even when I played games regularly, I rarely replayed any of these games. In many cases I only felt that I could play them once, as going back to them would lessen the original experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shadow-of-the-colossus&quot;&gt;Shadow of the Colossus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pdZQ98mWeto&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a child I was an avid reader. I read &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; at a young age, and while I didn’t care much for the meandering nature of the books, I appreciated the world-building and the grounded drama that ran throughout. I later became a regular movie-watcher, where I enjoyed &lt;em&gt;The Never Ending Story&lt;/em&gt;’s grim tale about depression and fighting back against a world that wants nothing but to oppress and destroy young spirits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d never experienced a game that got anywhere close to a similar experience until &lt;em&gt;Shadow of the Colossus&lt;/em&gt;, the best game that I’ve ever witnessed. I was chilled by the loneliness of the environments; awed by the technological capabilities of the coders building for a weak PlayStation 2 architecture; moved by the love driving the character to sacrifice so much for the princess; and driven to tears by the loss experienced by every character in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way that the weak gaming hardware was used as a plot device continues to impress me. The game world was barren because the console couldn’t handle anything more, but the plot provided a reason that made the minimal level design feel more acceptable: a dangerous creature was cut off from civilization to keep it chained and hidden. The game world was large and required horseback riding long distances because it was streaming from the disk and loading took a while, but the level design made it feel like a reasonable journey to a remote location that proved the commitment of the character. Having only one enemy at a time helped keep the already-struggling framerate stay at least somewhat playable most of the time, but making the enemies huge really fed into the fantasy story more than if they were merely a few feet taller than the main character. So much of this game was brilliantly executed, to the point that I have little interest in playing the remakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spec-ops-the-line&quot;&gt;Spec Ops: The Line&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wD661k1UpvQ&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; may get all the accolades for its plot twist, but I think &lt;em&gt;Spec Ops: The Line&lt;/em&gt; handles it twists in a more elegant and less frustrating manner. The concept of mental illness comes up often in games, but it tends to be used more as a gaming mechanic than primarily an element of the plot. I think that &lt;em&gt;Spec Ops: The Line&lt;/em&gt; tends to actually focus more on the plot, with some weaker gameplay and average graphics as a potential consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot is what makes it so much more interesting than &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt;, even though the latter has more inventive fighting, better voice acting across the cast, and better visual quality. Both games feature forced choices that punish the player for performing them, even though neither have alternatives built into the game, but &lt;em&gt;Spec Ops: The Line&lt;/em&gt; has both an omniscient narrator and side characters who cast doubt on the situation to serve as a proxy for the player, whereas &lt;em&gt;BioShock&lt;/em&gt; leaves much of that out of the game in the service of its plot twist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I especially appreciate the end of &lt;em&gt;Spec Ops: The Line&lt;/em&gt;, which provides one final choice that has chilling ramifications should one choose one of the options. It is a moment of very limited role-playing, but I appreciate its inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This game certainly has a lot of flaws and felt constrained by its budget, but the ambitions of the writer seemed to overpower much of the game’s limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;homeworld&quot;&gt;Homeworld&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pA7FbYAmrX0&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This game is unique on the list in that it depicts the actual destruction of the civilization rather than a retrospective of a long-dead culture. I was deeply moved by the experience of watching a nation fall and its survivors escape into the darkness, and it made every character death thereafter more painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plot definitely contains a thread of hope throughout it, but it’s weighed by the tragic loss at the start of the story, leavening everything with desperation and fear of an unknown enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uru-ages-beyond-myst&quot;&gt;Uru: Ages Beyond Myst&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 4/3&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9Ncw3t69Ze4&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t play much of the &lt;em&gt;Myst&lt;/em&gt; series before &lt;em&gt;Uru: Ages Beyond Myst&lt;/em&gt;, but we often as a family watched my father play the game to help come up with solutions for the complicated puzzles. I was fascinated by the world of &lt;em&gt;Myst&lt;/em&gt; more than I was the puzzles, and I thought &lt;em&gt;Uru: Ages Beyond Myst&lt;/em&gt; did a better job of building a world than any of the previous games. Better still are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mystjourney.com/riven/myst-novels/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;novelizations of the &lt;em&gt;Myst&lt;/em&gt; universe&lt;/a&gt;. An abandoned world from a dead civilization is always deeply interesting to me. I always wanted to know more about what caused the culture to collapse and the cities to empty, and &lt;em&gt;Uru&lt;/em&gt; helped explain a little more of that than the other games in the series. I especially liked the added realism of a three-dimensional game over the slideshows of some of the previous games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iron-helix&quot;&gt;Iron Helix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pDULUgKSVUw&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To continue on the “abandoned world by a dead civilization” theme, &lt;em&gt;Iron Helix&lt;/em&gt; was one of the first games that I played that had me solving puzzles related to the death of a crew on a spaceship protected by a drone that was going to attack any presence it detected. I liked finding the solution, but what intrigued me more was the logs of the crew uncovering some of the problems going on around the ship. I felt like I was involved in a world rather than solving a series of riddles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bastion--transistor&quot;&gt;Bastion / Transistor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mX48y24t9iU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RT55lch6y_U&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grouped these two games together because they almost feel like they come from a shared universe, but that’s probably more due to them sharing so many talented crew and cast between them, as they came from the same developer, one soon after the other. My preference is for &lt;em&gt;Bastion&lt;/em&gt;, as I think it had the more fulfilling plot of the two, but I do really appreciate the dying worlds of both. There is a mourning for what is lost in &lt;em&gt;Transistor&lt;/em&gt; that is missing somewhat in &lt;em&gt;Bastion&lt;/em&gt;, primarily because &lt;em&gt;Bastion&lt;/em&gt;’s world is so stylized that it doesn’t correlate well with reality; however, &lt;em&gt;Bastion&lt;/em&gt; has the more compelling resolution to its plot, in my opinion. I think I liked &lt;em&gt;Transistor&lt;/em&gt; more for the way the world was written out, the shadows of what once was being referenced in odd corners of the levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;halo-3-odst&quot;&gt;Halo 3: ODST&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WroxHMo6B_k&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one may seem like an odd addition to the list, but I was surprised by the loneliness and despair of this noir-like game. The audio vignettes from the other characters were quite a contrast from the destroyed city abandoned by its fleeing population, desperately seeking safety from an invading army. Being a secondary character to a much bigger story helped the war feel more comprehensive and somewhat distant, perhaps even unredeemable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;anarchy-online&quot;&gt;Anarchy Online&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MTQaTI4pQSk&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played &lt;em&gt;Anarchy Online&lt;/em&gt; when they switched to a free-to-play model for players who were interested in playing the levels that had been left empty by players who had moved on to newer and costly expansions. The game felt like a dead mall as a result of this separation. I walked the wide and barren streets of many sections of the free levels, noticing different areas where the level designers had expected crowds to form, and wondered what the city must have been like back when it was attractive to visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;journey--sky-children-of-the-light&quot;&gt;Journey / Sky: Children of the Light&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mU3nNT4rcFg&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/A3DNTfhUy0k&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story for these two games are extremely similar: a long-dead city is visited by a quiet explorer, who finds token of the people who once lived there; after some time, tragedy occurs and the explorer follows the people to a new life. &lt;em&gt;Journey&lt;/em&gt; aims for a single, simple story on that shared premises, and it concludes without answering much of the questions raised by the lore. &lt;em&gt;Sky: Children of the Light&lt;/em&gt; continues with that theme and adds more backstory to some success, though I find the level design ultimately more fulfilling than the developer’s attempts at building a cohesive world. Either way, there is something very poignant about the warm loneliness that the games elicit from me during my various visits to their worlds. Whenever I play them I long for more explanation for what was lost in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dear-esther--everybodys-gone-to-the-rapture&quot;&gt;Dear Esther / Everybody’s Gone to the Rapture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_pWBV6UTEyg&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/w1tBl7upgDU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading or hearing the stories of long-dead characters is apparently pretty captivating to me, because both of these games continue to haunt me years after seeing them. Especially captivating is the potentially repetitious pattern of existence subtly referenced in &lt;em&gt;Dear Esther&lt;/em&gt;, where characters seem to inhabit the same patterns of life throughout history, unknowingly repeating the mistakes of previous generations and ending up at the same island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience with &lt;em&gt;Everybody’s Gone to the Rapture&lt;/em&gt; is more limited as I’ve only watched the gameplay through videos, but it follows a similar theme of observing someone else’s loss while also processing one’s own in a way. It feels more like a radio play than &lt;em&gt;Dear Esther&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s still captivating to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching someone else play wasn’t unique to &lt;em&gt;Everybody’s Gone to the Rapture&lt;/em&gt;: as I have grown older, I have had less time to play any games of substance and have turned to Twitch and YouTube videos to keep up with the community that provided so much to me in my youth. The following games were consumed entirely through videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scorn&quot;&gt;Scorn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/i9eg7Pzk15g&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the H.R. Giger / Zdzisław Beksiński designs and fascination with the viscera of every creature in the game is taken to an uncomfortable extreme, but the depth of detail in building a ruined world is incredible and the skill in level and creature design is superb. I am repulsed by this game as much as I am in awe of it, so I tend to have to push aside all the awful elements to better appreciate the desolation depicted throughout the game. The sadness of the main character and the efforts to find resolution is an element that remains a thorn in my mind, months after watching the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;death-stranding&quot;&gt;DEATH STRANDING&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XcuFJXgU6cA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can thank Hideo Kojima for introducing me to Low Roar, a singer perfect for a sad and rainy drive. I suppose the theme of the game is more about building hope among a community than showcasing a lack of hope, but the world is deeply damaged, perhaps irrevocably, with only one man able to start threading things back together. I think the struggle to find purpose in a ruined world is one filled with despair, and many areas of the game felt deeply lonely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;soma&quot;&gt;SOMA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Rf4pAsNy_vA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a sad end to a world: to know the surface is burning and the survivors deep within the earth are dwindling and often seeking an end to it all. To struggle with one’s identity at the same time is deeply discouraging. I thought the horror elements of this game certainly provided opportunities to ponder what it was like to exist as one of those creatures, but I don’t think they added much to the gameplay. I wanted to know more about what the final moments on the surface were like, with more information about what caused all the fateful events to occur. I wanted to know what the general population thought when things &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SwXseZSjLsw&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all started to burn.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;returnal&quot;&gt;Returnal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flexNoWrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;flexItem&quot; style=&quot;aspect-ratio: 16/9&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Jv4BjWoB-NA&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I felt the full weight of hopelessness in this game until I contemplated what escaping the planet and living out as close to a normal life could mean, if death always meant a return to the planet. How horrible a fate that even death was no escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;i-do-smile-from-time-to-time&quot;&gt;I do smile from time to time&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose my fascination with the end of things and the reasons for everything failing might seem like I am a miserable person to be around, but I don’t welcome oblivion; I much prefer to live in a society that is growing or thriving than I am to live in one near its end. As much as I have enjoyed playing games with post-apocalyptic themes, I don’t relish the thought of these events ever occurring in reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have learned from these games — and this may seem like an odd lesson, but I do think there is a connection — is that hope requires effort. Without striving for improvement, we all slide towards annihilation. Submitting to hopelessness will ruin us all, even if the villains or predicaments in our lives &lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt; unbeatable. I think that is why I often pay attention to local and national politics, as I am worried for the future of the country and for all the people who live in it, even those who don’t act or look like me. These games have shown me that hopelessness is easy; it’s the default position of any person who has given up their agency and accepted the abyss. True heroism comes from finding hope within that chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t registered to vote, please &lt;a href=&quot;https://turbovote.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;do so today.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


            
            
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2023/04/25/hopelessness-in-video-games.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2023/04/25/hopelessness-in-video-games.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The time for analog clocks is over</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;I don’t like analog clocks. People have tried to persuade me and have shown me the obvious benefits to using such a platform, but I continue to remain unconvinced and I feel that I have good reason for my opinion. I will now present a rather adversarial and controversial view of why analog clocks are inferior to the newer digital clock method of presenting time. This will be a pedantic and antagonistic position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am part of a shameful selection of adults who find little value in the modern-day use of the analog clock. I never set it as a goal to find myself in opposition to the existence of the analog clock, but I have to accept now that my continued confusion is likely permanent. I realize that by being in such a slim minority of people in the world that I will likely not find a sympathetic ear, but this will not silence me. I will not self-censor just because such a huge amount of people find no issue with what troubles me. This is the internet, the year 2023, and I am an American white male who has considered making his own podcast. Everything is permitted for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the appeal of selecting a tool less efficient for the job? Some people like the performative or meditative aspects of many hobbies and tasks, making a point of the time spent on the task compared to its comparatively mindless modern automated method. But for the average user, is the use of an analog clock rooted in art or contemplation, or is it rather on average to find out the time of day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps my issue is rooted in the way that I perceive the purpose and working of the analog clock. The average analog clock displays the hours and minutes using two hands, one for each element of time. When one wishes to look at the time on the analog clock, it is performed by looking at both hands and perceiving their proximity to a number or dash running along the edge of the clock’s surface. Both hands must be seen to accurately understand the current time, and the passage of time dynamically changes the position of those information-giving hands throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, a digital clock presents the time in a left-to-right hour:minute pattern that does not change in position, requires no guessing or deciphering of what combination of number/letter/dash refers to the hours and minutes on the face of the clock, and can be shrunk to sizes smaller than an analog clock without obfuscating the detail it is attempting to present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually look at an analog clock in an hour:minute method, which may be my first mistake. I expect to see an hour hand pointing to the current hour, rather than giving me a semi-accurate approximation of the time distance between the current hour and the next. If the time is 7:55, I struggle knowing if the hand is pointing toward the seven or the eight. I then look at the minute hand, which is actually pointing directly at its intended digit instead of being somewhere vague. I usually read that analog clock, then, as “8:55 — wait no, uh, 7:55? Yes, 7:55.”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why make an hour hand perform the task of both the hour and minute hand and then include a minute hand whose task is solely to display minutes? Why not have an analog clock that displays one hand over the current actual hour and then have a minute hand point to the current minute? The hour hand is the only hand on the clock, even including the second hand, that doesn’t point to its intended target aside from maybe five minutes in an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t make sense to cling to this archaic and inefficient method of timekeeping any longer. Please join me in advocating for this silly aspect of one’s life and becoming a tyrant like I have, externalizing my own weaknesses by moaning about other people’s choices.&lt;/p&gt;

            
                
                    &lt;h4&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
                    &lt;ul&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0QVPUIRGthI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dave Allen - ”Teaching Your Kid Time (1993)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                
            
            
        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2023/02/23/analog-clocks.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2023/02/23/analog-clocks.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Flooding and school shootings</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;The fragility of life is rarely more realized than in the moments surrounding a natural disaster. In the normalcy of daily routines, we all can fall numb to the potential dangers present in our world. To stay vigilant would be exhausting, so we avoid considering them until the signs of something terrible approaching are too obvious to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people handle the burden of watching by making it their occupation. They look for the signs and share it with the rest of the population, hoping to avert disaster. The general public then takes those findings into consideration and changes or adapts to handle the oncoming issue. This has helped humanity overcome hardship and avert disaster throughout its more recent history, sparing the lives of millions and allowing for greater progress and stability in many countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember hearing the criticism of Houston’s city planning when the hurricane flooded many city streets: how the draining system was not prepared, how the homes were not built at an appropriate height from the street, and how the systems to mitigate flooding weren’t maintained well in advance of the storm. In the aftermath, people expected efforts to be made to prevent future disaster. Homes were built taller and flood plains were given better consideration. There was a measure of learned helplessness in the reaction, though: too much of the city infrastructure was already built to change it to adapt to the new information and experience gained from the flooding. Only a limited reaction could be produced as a response to the flooding, but those actions were taken. It wasn’t a question; people wanted to never let this happen again, but their options were restricted because of the cost to change the existing infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now consider the way that we react countrywide to school shootings. Little is set in stone — or concrete, if one were to compare the laws and systems around gun use in the United States to the infrastructure of Houston. We can adapt to new information and new experiences and learn from them to make a better system for our children. Yet in each instance, we instead react as if there are fewer options available to us than what Houstonians were presented. Incredibly, many actually suggest adding additional guns into the situation, as if adding more water to a flood would help prevent flooding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New technology and methods are regularly introduced to communities to better handle future weather and flooding events, to forecast the danger, and how to respond to it. Gun safety, on the contrary, seems to be a completely preventable man-made issue. Clear signs of its dangerous elements are evident through existing data and methods to prevent it are already in law around the world. What is it about so many of our political leaders that they would seek to cause harm to their constituents, and why do those constituents ignore their contradictory behavior? Is it not in their best interest to look to the helpers, hear their cries, and adapt to avoid the danger? Isn’t living enough of a danger in itself? Why add to our problems by encouraging further harm to us and our children?&lt;/p&gt;

            
                
                    &lt;h4&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
                    &lt;ul&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b5ykNZl9mTQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Back-To-School Essentials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0IM4p62p3M0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Generation Lockdown — March for Our Lives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yTCXGAeLGHw&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;We Gave a Speech to Wayne LaPierre at the NRA Convention&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                
            
            &lt;p class=&quot;embedtool&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v-qj2rqgChM&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;Channel 5 with Andrew Callaghan&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v-qj2rqgChM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NRA Conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;In this episode, we cover the recent National Rifle Association meeting and exhibition which occurred between May 27-29 at George R. Brown Convention Center in Houston, TX, just days after the tragic mass shooting at Robb Elementary School in Uvalde which took the lives of 19 students and 2 teachers, as well as travel to Uvalde, TX to talk to locals affected by the tragedy.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2022/09/23/school-shootings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2022/09/23/school-shootings.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Parasocial relationships are weird</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Parasocial relationships are strange. They feel closer than some friendships but are hollow facsimiles, barely reaching beyond the level of acquaintance. They are unequal connections. They do not mutually benefit all participants. Why then does losing a connection to a stranger feel nearly as bittersweet as a true bond with a known companion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve lost real friends before. I now am mostly left with the parasocial relationships, so when they end they feel as poignant as the real friendships. They are mutually connected to an interest as well, so getting to an age or part of my life where I lose that interest or can’t commit to it as much any longer can feel like a betrayal to a friendship that doesn’t truly exist. It’s not as if the friendships lack any real value; in many cases it has been those friendships and the communities surrounding them that has kept me grounded to something consistent and trustworthy so that the less-reliable areas of my life feel more manageable. When those communities, either through my own actions or those on the other side of the relationship, begin to feel less reliable, I realize how little I have available to fill the gaps in my life and I feel guilty and lonely for depending on the parasocial and sad because I’m now truly alone. There’s a sense of shame that I ever found anything of value in the parasocial because it was only a placebo, a panacea for a problem that I could’ve spent time solving through true connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do I find those connections, though? Is it the ease of finding parasocial connections that make them so tempting? Am I doomed to forever be looking back on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Gvk0_6p_-s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;good old days&lt;/a&gt; and the strong relationships they offered? Or is this the part of my life where I &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.robkhenderson.com/past-newsletter/the-seasons-of-a-mans-life-a-review&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;no longer get to enjoy those types of friendships&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;tiktok-embed&quot; cite=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@thejoemolloyshow/video/7092489908622773547&quot; data-video-id=&quot;7092489908622773547&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 605px;&quot;&gt;

&lt;section&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;@thejoemolloyshow&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@thejoemolloyshow&quot;&gt;@thejoemolloyshow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/@thejoemolloyshow/video/7092489908622773547&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;word-break: break-all&quot;&gt;https://www.tiktok.com/@thejoemolloyshow/video/7092489908622773547&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence: Every podcast hosted by guys or “weekend warrior” type retreat. They’re all trying to replace loneliness with some “bro code” Be lonely. Find purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;♬ original sound - Joe Molloy&quot; href=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/music/original-sound-7092489905506601774&quot;&gt;♬ original sound - Joe Molloy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/section&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://www.tiktok.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I do despair that I have not yet found a community in Oklahoma City, I haven’t fully given up hope that things will change. For now I am settling with the weirdness of parasocial relationships, but I do think it’s possible to find new friends in middle age, even if it ends up being more of the mentor-based relationship with someone younger than me. I’m quite a bit of an introvert — a problem of its own when attempting to find new friends — so I think I can manage on my own for a while, but I do miss having a group of people to call my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A less painful element of my changing life is the loss of interests that used to deeply engage me. I used to be quite a big video game fan and collected a large amount of games and game consoles in my little apartment; however, once I met my future wife I stopped finding them as engaging. I didn’t mind losing that part of my life, but I didn’t realize how much of my community and friendships were based on that shared interest. Similarly, when I moved into board games and started buying a collection of long-form and rule-rich versions, I found in my community of friends a group of people equally interested who encouraged me to try out new games and explore new genres. When I moved away, my interest in board games begin to wane, and I found them more to be a painful reminder of what I once had rather than a comfort to me or a hopeful reminder of the community I could have again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to rebuild my interests but time and community seems limited to me now. I feel more boring to others and less capable of becoming something more interesting, which makes it harder for me to feel capable of being able to make a contribution to a new community. I want to be available for my wife, my children, and my job, but I fear that leaves me little time to seek out a series of strong friendships (or perhaps even one). While I haven’t figuratively scooped out my interests or hobbies from my identity, I wonder if returning to them would feel as fulfilling as I remember or if they would in the end feel alien to me. Would I be regressing in my personal growth? What should I like as the person I am now? What am I now if I lack the strength in my current interests that I used to have in my previous hobbies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am probably overthinking this. Maybe that’s why parasocial relationships are so popular and attractive: they’re simpler and less complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

            
            &lt;p class=&quot;embedtool&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5ev8HzogFgs&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;Giant Bomb&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5ev8HzogFgs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TheRitual.mp4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Change is afoot at Giant Bomb… the team must turn to the dark arts and enact an unholy ritual to bring back videogames.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.giantbomb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Giant Bomb&lt;/a&gt; used to be the source of much entertainment and community. Throughout the years I have seen many of the staff leave in one way or another, including the most recent upsets over the past year that included the majority of the original staff leaving to start their own ventures. It’s strange to watch them all leave and realize that I&apos;ve changed, too: I no longer play games outside of Apple Arcade and even got rid of my gaming PC. Gaming used to be a big part of my life and a large part of my community, but due to lack of time and waning interest, I have become a distant observer, like visiting an old neighborhood and finding it alien and unfamiliar.&lt;/p&gt;

        </description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2022/06/22/parasocial-relationships.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2022/06/22/parasocial-relationships.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Feeling stuck</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to tell you of a grave error that I made several years ago that has haunted me ever since. Dear reader, you must read of my mistake so that you don’t fall into the same trap as me and ruin your life like I’ve ruined mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So please, if there is one bit of advice that you take from my writing, please may it be this: stop learning immediately. Gaining knowledge will only lead you to sorrow. You will never be happier than you are now by learning about the things that intrigue you. The act of investigation will expose your mind to nuance, new possibilities, difficult realities, and discomfort that you didn’t believe imaginable, and it will permanently change you for the worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop now. Hit the back button. Close the tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-one-it-starts-small-but-then-it-festers&quot;&gt;Part one: it starts small, but then it festers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think my journey to pain started with the architecture in my neighborhood of Bartlesville, Oklahoma. I noticed that many new structures being built near the main highway lacked good design designs to benefit the community in which they were placed. They lacked friendly entranceways or pleasant views from the sides, or were so stripped of design that they felt inhuman and otherworldly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started searching for answers online and discovered the non-profit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strongtowns.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Strong Towns&lt;/a&gt;, which gave me many of the words that I needed to describe my discomfort. They taught me about city planning issues that sidetracked progress in most cities across the country, which helped me see how my dissatisfaction with modern building styles was linked to a greater systemic problem than just ugly modern building styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now supplied with better terms and historical data, I saw my neighborhood in a new way: a conflict between the relics maintained from a previous set of policies and the new structures bound by modern zoning laws and lobbying. The attitudes enforcing this dissonance went beyond the accidental destruction of community or collective thinking and into more personal issues like politics and beliefs. I could see more clearly how many of these elements of our lives were interconnected and function in a tension of both communion and contradiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should’ve stopped there. I should have accepted that what seemed so simple — &lt;em&gt;just build better buildings, and everything will be okay!&lt;/em&gt; — was merely only a result of a gnarled set of requirements from city and state building codes for reasons that I would never understand. Nevertheless, I continued searching and grew no happier from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;embedtool&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OQE_5MFCekg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed how many of my normal experiences were shaped by automobiles. Downtown areas that were seemed most memorable to me were dominated by foot traffic, and some of my lasting experiences were reachable by subway or train. Why then was my average day defined by the car?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I lived in Houston I regularly took the bus (and bicycle) to get to work. It was not a difficult walk to take and the bus system was adequate for my needs — in fact, if I wished to take a particular route, the bus would drop me off right at the entrance to the office. Yet, when I mentioned that I took the bus, my coworkers were alarmed. They wondered if I had car problems and marveled that I had traveled on it by choice. They had to sit in slow-moving and dangerous traffic for long stretches of time, yet I had someone drive me to work for under two dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not as if Houston’s bus system was superb; while it did get overhauled and greatly improved on its area of fulfillment, it did not parallel the transit systems of other more modern cities. Houston is built like a giant suburb, so the bus had to take circuitous routes through neighborhoods to avoid the large arterial roads and frequently had to struggle with traffic weaving around nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recalled the experience I had in Seoul, South Korea, traveling across its large expanse by subway. I was able to do so much traveling in a few short days because of the expansive and comprehensive subway system, along with its tight integration with payment services that made boarding simple. I began seeking out stories of transit systems in other countries, which is how I discovered a large community of YouTube channels and Twitter accounts that discuss this very issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving transit and housing seemed possible in the United States — so why did it seem that nobody was interested in the change? Why did so many of my fellow residents seemed to respond with a measure of disdain when I suggested we consider the experiences of other countries and implement the results of the work in our own communities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when I began to hit the wall of politics and lobbying that stifle our options in the United States. If you haven’t yet taken my advice and stopped reading this to prevent any possible learning from happening, please take this advice and never look into the politics or political history of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-two-it-gets-worse&quot;&gt;Part two: it gets worse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heeded no advice and widened my considerations to the politics of my community. I learned of the people in power that formed the decisions to prevent certain others from entering neighborhoods and limit the capabilities of the counter-cultural groups to make change from within. I saw how &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/behind-the-bastards/id1373812661?i=1000552566122&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;religious&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/behind-the-bastards/id1373812661?i=1000552806645&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;political&lt;/a&gt; extremism had hurt and damaged communities throughout the United States, not just Bartlesville, Oklahoma. Suddenly my problem expanded from “I wish at least the downtown area of this little city was more friendly to people living in it” to “the United States seems hostile to anyone who isn’t following its particular cultural normative state.” See? No happiness can come from learning like me. Problems get bigger, more difficult to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these abusive histories have been forgotten and the culture that exists in its wake are considered standard or ordinary, acceptable to most. We don’t know what we’re missing — or rather, most of us don’t, until we begin to ask questions (which you should never do, as I’ve already stated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it seems like this is all spiraling bigger and bigger and that there’s a general encroaching sense of doom to all my writing, then I want to congratulate you on your fine reading skills. I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; been battling just that very feeling, which I’m sure is either part of the plan or a side-effect of understanding too much about the plan, I’m not sure which. Either way, I think you might find it better to be siding with ignorance than with knowledge, if my general state of mind is of any indication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know — should anyone learn what I have learned? Is it good for me to know these things and to think what I do now? Do I feel better? Would I want to go back to ignorance? It’s not really a worthwhile line of questioning for me to have, but I certainly have asked myself this many times. That’s why I’ve penned this plaintive post to you, admonishing your desire to learn more and to instead encourage you to be as stupid as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I’ve been trying to be nonchalant and chipper and funny about my journey because I don’t want to be another person sharing an experience in a maudlin way, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gawker.com/culture/the-pity-me-personal-essay&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;as this tends to annoy some readers&lt;/a&gt;, but I feel that I must be more honest and share feelings in a more accurate fashion. The path I’ve taken in the past few years has changed me dramatically and now I feel adrift. I no longer have the community I once saw as my own and I have yet to find a comfortable new one. Oklahoma has been my home for a decade and yet I’ve never felt so out of place within it. I think it was when I found myself reading a website on emigration that I realized how foreign I feel now and how desperate I am to find a place that feels right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to be honest with my situation, though. I don’t have a job that offers me the financial mobility to move to another state, never mind another country. The low cost of living in Oklahoma is both a blessing and a curse. I also don’t want to disrupt my wife’s first good chance at a community with her network of friends, a success that I’ve not experienced for many years. Three children makes a move a far more difficult process to complete, and each successive trip has felt more daunting than the last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I feel that I’m stuck in Oklahoma, in its regressive policies, its suburbia, and its heat. I want to escape it, but to where? And will anywhere else be better? Will I actually find the thing for which I am earnestly seeking, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.robkhenderson.com/past-newsletter/the-seasons-of-a-mans-life-a-review&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;and if I did would I actually be happy?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://www.robkhenderson.com/past-newsletter/the-seasons-of-a-mans-life-a-review&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book goes on to state that this kind of reappraisal can’t be a cool, rational, intellectual process. To fully evolve beyond this stage, a man must experience the emotional turmoil, despair, and inner conflict involved with questioning his current life structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of men Levinson interviewed in this period thought of their lives thus far as either a flawed success or a failure. This is because few of them accomplished everything they thought they would by this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their outcomes usually fell below their hopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the outcome was typically good enough that very few men considered the direction they had taken to be a total disaster. In fact, many acknowledged that others thought their lives were quite favorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, even the men who did accomplish all they set out to were generally not as satisfied as they’d hoped. The book describes this as “one of the most pervasive illusions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For men, dealing with the consequences of the fact that fulfilling their ambitions did not give them true happiness is often “a mind-boggling process.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Robert Henderson: The Seasons of a Man’s Life—A Review&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to be older and depressed. I don’t want to spend every day viewing my current city of residence in such a negative way, especially when I consider my advantages and privileges in life. Who am I to complain? I want to change my mindset to something approaching acceptance without bending my identity, a comfortable ease amidst a troubling direction, to be able to accept that there are plenty of things wrong around me but that I shouldn’t lose hope that it can get better. I have to be the change in my community instead of abandoning it, but I fight against a miserable sense of despair and isolation every day. Working through that mental sludge to do something productive has been a difficult process for me and I’m nowhere near making it a regular practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.robkhenderson.com/past-newsletter/the-seasons-of-a-mans-life-a-review&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;book review I linked&lt;/a&gt; claims that my frustration and ennui might be linked to the feeling that one’s life lacks the meaning that was once originally assumed. I think this might be the true source of my feelings of isolation. I do find meaning in being a husband and father, but I also worry that believing those things to be my sole purpose is being a coward. Isn’t that just living a default life? Is not wanting more not living in fear? It’s a life rich with good memories and fun experiences, but I worry that existence isn’t enough for me to feel satisfied that I used the years I have wisely. When I see the amount of suffering I feel ashamed to ever find fulfillment in my own richly-lived existence when I could also find a way to help improve the life of someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There really isn’t a conclusion to this entry. I have no advice yet to give as I’m still figuring it all out for myself. I do have a general goal, though: to feel better by accepting my place as a misfit. I want to be in the community to help change it for the better. But unfortunately, I believe that also means making other people uncomfortable by teaching them to learn, too.&lt;/p&gt;


            
            &lt;p class=&quot;embedtool&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WcsuyMWmRRU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;blueathena&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WcsuyMWmRRU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lauren Zuniga, &quot;To the Oklahoma Progressives Plotting Mass Exodus&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Lauren Zuniga performs her poem &quot;To the Oklahoma Progressives Plotting Mass Exodus&quot; on December 17, 2010, at a Blue Moon House Concert.  Video recorded and edited by Laura Anne Heller of Blue Athena Productions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe allow=&quot;autoplay *; encrypted-media *; fullscreen *&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; style=&quot;border-radius: .5rem; width: 100%; overflow: hidden; background: transparent&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-forms allow-popups allow-same-origin allow-scripts allow-storage-access-by-user-activation allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot; src=&quot;https://embed.podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/pod-save-america/id1192761536?i=1000564083073&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;Pod Save America&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/pod-save-america/id1192761536?i=1000564083073&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&quot;Why We Can&apos;t Give Up.&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The U.S. Senate debates gun safety reform following the horrific school shooting at a Texas elementary school and Senator Alex Padilla joins to talk about what else can be done to stop mass shootings. And later, Jon and Dan go through Tuesday&apos;s election results from the primaries in Georgia and Texas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2022/06/10/feeling-stuck.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2022/06/10/feeling-stuck.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I used to be anxious about being thought of as ignorant</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;Everything seems simpler when one is young. I was driven in my youth by a pursuit of moral truths that I believed could be applied to all absolutely and unilaterally, equalizing all injustices and eliminating all suffering. I was certain I was capable of understanding these truths and that I had already accomplished much in finding them. It did seem coincidentally beneficial that these moral truths were so well in line with my own preconceived mental models and cultural background, but I assumed more that I was being transformed to the truths rather than they were being formed from my own worldview and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my efforts to gain more knowledge of objective truth I began to seek out deeper understanding from my peers. I first started with family and friends who I knew to have spent time considering the philosophical and moral issues of the day. The answers I received did regularly challenge me but still largely conformed to my preexisting understanding of the world. Still not sated, I went beyond to apologists and philosophers within my community. The answers I found there were more convoluted and figurative which made them feel more impressive and rational, satisfying an underlying anxiety about being able to have a convincing answer to every question. Believing that I had found the panacea, I ruminated on their answers (and my new-found intellectual superiority), deeply pondering the variety of my reactions to what I heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answers certainly sounded good in repetition in my mind, but they felt weak and embarrassing whenever I found the opportunity to share them in conversation. So much discussion and defining of terms had to be performed before reaching the answer to help make sense of them, and even then the listener was not likely to be convinced. The answers began to feel hollow and speculative to me. I knew then that I needed to question an even wider source, one willing to more fully criticize itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was to the people who challenged every answer in the tree down to the root that I turned. What I learned frightened and angered me at the same time: I discovered that my previous sources for answers had failed to ask the important question, “What if I’m wrong?” — not of just the supposed answer to the question, but of the mental framework that supplied the answers, which I was discovering with worrying regularity were more based on presuppositions than with well-researched explanations. The previous answers to my questions therefore worked as long as the sources of the answers never were challenged, which was disquieting to me because I wasn’t seeking a panacea for my curiosity but rather for absolute truth on which to align my worldview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of questioning myself was agonizing. I felt furious that these self-criticisms were not encouraged within my denser social network and that I had never been exposed to this type of consideration before. I recalled every time in my life where this sort of questioning was seen as dangerous to truth, yet I was discovering more solid foundations for my worldview in this harrowing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned that I was not alone in this particular journey: I found that others had asked these same questions generations before. People far more educated and experienced than me had spent years of their lives researching and discussing possibilities that I had never even considered as answers to my questions. I saw that where I had charted myself on my search for absolute truth was grossly over-calculated. I watched my universe of understanding become dwarfed by the breadth of what could be learned and realized with a mixture of dread and resignation that I was nowhere near the end of my journey; in fact, I began to accept that I would likely never unearth some answers within my lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I had more answers than ever before, with explanations that made sense and that could be shared without feeling a sense of discomfort or fear. The answers that could not be given made more sense as to why they were unanswerable. My anxiety disappeared; I no longer felt foolish for not knowing something, for admitting ignorance was the first step to learning. Instead of feeling a deep need to have all the answers about what was true, I could instead stay quiet and listen for potential better truths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accepting all of this greatly eased my anxieties and calmed me in ways that I hadn’t felt in years. I finally began to understand the book of the Bible often titled &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://biblia.com/books/nrsv/Ec9.9-10&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ecclesiastes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which before often depressed me due to its nihilistic tones. Before now I never could grasp the dissonace of the author’s intent to cheapen the life of a person while also claiming that joy could be found within it. I comprehend its message more clearly now: by admitting my ignorance of some things I can turn my focus to the present experiences of life, gaining meaning from the moments that I can understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote cite=&quot;https://biblia.com/books/nrsv/Ec9.9-10&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy life with the wife whom you love, all the days of your vain life that are given you under the sun, because that is your portion in life and in your toil at which you toil under the sun. Whatever your hand finds to do, do with your might; for there is no work or thought or knowledge or wisdom in Sheol, to which you are going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Ecclesiastes 9:9–10 (New Revised Standard Version)&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of tying myself up trying to understand the things that I cannot know, I can see now the meaning to be found in the things that can be understood — and those things are all around me right now. I am no longer ashamed to be ignorant of the things that I cannot know for I am working to be too busy enjoying the things that I can.&lt;/p&gt;


            
            &lt;p class=&quot;embedtool&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL1mr9ZTZb3TUeQHe-lZZF2DTxDHA_LFxi&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;InspiringPhilosophy&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL1mr9ZTZb3TUeQHe-lZZF2DTxDHA_LFxi&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Genesis 1–11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of the first sources I encountered that really challenged me to consider possibilities and worldviews foreign to my own while still working within my larger worldview. This video series helped me feel more comfortable about seeking out wider sources than I had ever before considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;outbound m1p5&quot;&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;button&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL1mr9ZTZb3TUeQHe-lZZF2DTxDHA_LFxi&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;emoji&quot;&gt;🎥&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;Watch the playlist&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

        </description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2022/02/03/anxious-about-being-ignorant.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2022/02/03/anxious-about-being-ignorant.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Now on Jekyll</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;I’ve spent the past few days moving my little site here from hand-written HTML to &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a blogging platform that can build into HTML files very similar to ones that I was writing before, but without all the hard work of maintaining code throughout each page. Now I can write posts in a simpler fashion and start to add new features like an &lt;a href=&quot;https://dhepworth.github.io/feed.xml&quot;&gt;Atom/RSS feed&lt;/a&gt; with greater ease than if I continued coding everything by hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been wanting to add on more to the site as time goes on but doing it all by hand was going to potentially grow exponentially difficult. I wanted the freedom to test out new designs that remained consistent throughout the site, so each new bit of content I added would only increase my update time. I originally expected the text to largely serve as a placeholder, but I also began to enjoy the writing process required to make a new post and wanted to save my work rather than overwrite it with each update. Jekyll had seemed like a nice idea in the past but I felt I didn’t have a good reason to use it and that it would probably be more difficult to set up than what was promised. The latter part was true, but not by much. Setting up my computer to begin using Jekyll actually took longer and was more frustrating than coding in the language it uses.&lt;/p&gt;


            
            
        </description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2021/12/22/jekyll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2021/12/22/jekyll.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We aren’t asking the right questions</title>
        <author>David Hepworth</author>
        <description>
            &lt;p&gt;The penultimate episode of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/podcasts/rise-and-fall-of-mars-hill/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Rise &amp;amp; Fall of Mars Hill&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is a frustrating investigatory experience. The show presents to the listener the evidence of an abusive pastor in a permissive church system, building the case that this was an ongoing problem within the organization that eventually collapsed under the weight of the trauma dealt within. What I believe the episode fails to do and has continued to do throughout the series is to follow that evidence to its obvious conclusion, despite the pretense of seeking answers for how it all happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this episode, host Mike Cosper presents the possibility that celebrity culture is causing people to become blind to the long-term abuse that some pastors like Mark Driscoll can bring down on church staff and members. Cosper’s view is that only the widely popular pastors (or those with large enough audiences that grow beyond the borders of their own church) can distort the view of their importance amongst their followers, leading to greater freedom to abuse people without reprimand. This is an interesting theory and could explain some occurrences, but I would contend that this is definitely not the primary issue driving the abuse. A dictatorial level of control can be exerted on members from a pastor whose town is barely more than an intersection of two small roads. The size of the church does not matter nor does the popularity of the pastor determine the effect he has on his followers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that the answer lies in the power structure built within the Christian church. The ability to teach others about the Bible is seen as an ability gifted by God. Church members often believe that these teaching skills, as being from God, extend into areas not in the scope of Biblical teaching. The level of power a pastor can have over his church members can grow into incredibly sensitive areas of church members’ lives. I don’t think that this exertion of power is a corruption of once-proper teaching; I think that this is a flaw built into the original interpretation of Biblical church structure within Evangelical Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This flaw is evident in how Mark Driscoll’s abuse was handled. The kind of abuse Mark Driscoll committed should have been seen immediately as non-Christian in its behavior. &lt;em&gt;But Mark Driscoll is still a pastor.&lt;/em&gt; There should be no equivocation among anyone that abusers like these are committing acts that go against the stated moralities of Christianity. I know Christians are dismayed and appalled when abusers are caught, but then &lt;em&gt;nothing seems to be learned from these events to prevent them from happening again.&lt;/em&gt; Christians across the country should be in crisis, seeking to uncover these problems and stop them before they can ever happen again. This is a disaster for Christianity, but people are not reacting at the level necessary to make change or even seem deeply troubled. What should one deduce from the limited reactions from Christians about pastoral abuse, if not that these traumatic events are just the standard costs of operating a religious non-profit within the Evangelical Christian community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about the way that Evangelical Christians view other religions, denominations, or communities that have morals, cultures, or rites that differ from their own. Is holistic grace applied to all followers of that alternative worldview when one or two within that community commit some immoral act? Do Christians respond with such muted reactions when someone outside of their own community does something that goes against what they proclaim to be the morality found in the Bible? How can it not be seen as anything but hypocrisy to judge harshly those outside the Christian community for their faults but regulatorily ignore the faults within? How can one judge the moral standards set by Evangelical Christianity as being true and good if those proclaiming those standards don‘t respect them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this podcast is missing and I think Evangelical Christianity lacks in these moments of abuse allegations is self-reflection, self-blame, and a willingness to change in any dramatic or permanent fashion. Too much energy is spent attempting to convert the world at large to the Christian mindset when more should be focused on on ensuring that people are not abused by immoral acts within the Christian churches. I think a blasé response to pastoral abuse does much to harm the reputation of Christianity and fosters disillusionment and resentment within. Fundamental problems with Evangelical Christian culture might not be the source of pastoral abuse, but I wish I would hear it considered by people in authority within the culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;emoji&quot;&gt;🧵&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Update: I listened to the final episode.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;m1&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I’m listening to the last episode of The Rise &amp;amp; Fall of Mars Hill now, but I have to take it in pieces because my nerves can’t handle long stretches of it. I’ve written about it in the past and so I’m starting to grow tired of it, but I want to conclude things here (for now).&lt;/p&gt;— David Hepworth 😷💉 (@DHPersonal) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DHPersonal/status/1469169177709662212?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 10, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


            
                
                    &lt;h4&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
                    &lt;ul&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bethallisonbarr.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Making of Biblical Womenhood: How the Subjegation of Women Became Gospel Truth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://baptistnews.com/article/i-lived-in-the-culture-of-the-rise-and-fall-of-mars-hill-and-theres-one-part-of-the-story-thats-wrong&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;I lived in the culture of ‘The Rise and Fall of Mars Hill,’ and there’s one part of the story that’s wrong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
                    
                    &lt;/ul&gt;
                
            
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe allow=&quot;autoplay *; encrypted-media *; fullscreen *&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; style=&quot;border-radius: .5rem; width: 100%; overflow: hidden; background: transparent&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-forms allow-popups allow-same-origin allow-scripts allow-storage-access-by-user-activation allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation&quot; src=&quot;https://embed.podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/the-tempest/id1569401963?i=1000541655003&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4 class=&quot;m0&quot;&gt;&lt;cite class=&quot;dash&quot;&gt;Christianity Today&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/podcasts/rise-and-fall-of-mars-hill/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Rise &amp;amp; Fall of Mars Hill&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;The Tempest: Episode 11&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t one thing that ended Mars Hill. It was one thing after another, after another, after another&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;outbound&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;button&quot; href=&quot;https://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/podcasts/rise-and-fall-of-mars-hill/tempest-mars-hill-driscoll.html&quot; id=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;emoji&quot;&gt;🎧&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;Listen now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        </description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2021/11/26/we-arent-asking-the-right-questions.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://dhepworth.github.io/post/2021/11/26/we-arent-asking-the-right-questions.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>